<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE merge [ <!ENTITY fo-related "pdf/postscript/rtf"> ]>
<!-- $Id: autopoweroff.xml,v 1.10 2005/10/16 18:28:55 deragon Exp $ -->
<document>

<document-meta-info>
  <title>Autopoweroff: User Guide</title>
  <attribute name="Author"><a href="mailto:hans@deragon.biz">Hans Deragon</a></attribute>
  <attribute name="Company"><a href="http://www.deragon.biz">Deragon Informatique inc.</a></attribute>
  <attribute name="Revision">$Revision: 1.10 $</attribute>
  <attribute name="Last Modified">$Date: 2005/10/16 18:28:55 $</attribute>
</document-meta-info>

<!-- formating info -->
<document-formatting-info>
  <stylesheet url="style.css" />
  <left-margin>40pt</left-margin>
  <right-margin>40pt</right-margin>
  <top-margin>20pt</top-margin>
  <bottom-margin>25pt</bottom-margin>
  <body-font-family>Helvetica</body-font-family>
  <body-font-size>12pt</body-font-size>
  <document-title-font-family>Helvetica</document-title-font-family>
  <document-title-font-size>16pt</document-title-font-size>
  <document-attributes-font-family>Helvetica</document-attributes-font-family>
  <document-attributes-font-size>12pt</document-attributes-font-size>
  <section-header-font-family>Helvetica</section-header-font-family>
  <generate-section-numbers>yes</generate-section-numbers>
  <header-height>75pt</header-height>
  <footer-height>50pt</footer-height>
</document-formatting-info>

<!-- document header -->
<!--
<document-header>
<table width="100%"><tr><td align="left"><img src="logo_auriga.gif" alt="Aurigalogic: Smart Business Solutions"/></td>
<td valign="middle" align="right"><b>Autopoweroff: User Guide</b></td></tr>
</table>
<hr size="1" color="red" noshade="true" />
</document-header>
-->
<document-header>
<table width="100%"><tr><td align="left">
  <a href="http://www.deragon.biz">Deragon Informatique inc.</a>
</td>
<td valign="middle" align="right">
<b>Autopoweroff: User Guide</b>
<br/>
<a href="http://autopoweroff.sourceforge.net"><img src="http://sourceforge.net/sflogo.php?group_id=77254&amp;type=1" width="88" height="31" border="0" alt="SourceForge.net Logo"/></a>
</td></tr>
</table>
<hr size="1" color="red" noshade="true" />
</document-header>

<document-body>
<!-- meta info -->
<table-of-content>
<link href="#what_is">About Autopoweroff</link>
<link href="#distributions">Supported Linux distributions</link>
<link href="#download">Download</link>
<link href="#configuration">Screenshots &amp; Configuration
  <link href="#config_autopoweroff">Autopoweroff configuration
    <link href="#config_autopoweroff_gui">Autopoweroff GUI configuration tool</link>
    <link href="#config_autopoweroff_file">Autopoweroff configuration file (autopoweroff.conf)</link>
  </link>
  <link href="#config_bios">BIOS configuration</link>
</link>
<link href="#installation">Installation</link>
<link href="#uninstallation">Uninstallation</link>
<link href="#license">License</link>
<link href="#troubleshooting">Troubleshooting
  <link href="#troubleshooting_glade">Troubleshooting Glade warnings
  </link>
</link>
<link href="#developers">For developers</link>
<link href="#todo">To do</link>
<link href="#change_history">Change History
  <link href="#changes_3.0.0">Version 2.9.0</link>
  <link href="#changes_2.1.0">Version 2.1.0</link>
  <link href="#changes_2.0.0">Version 2.0.0</link>
  <link href="#changes_1.2.0">Version 1.2.0</link>
  <link href="#changes_1.1.1">Version 1.1.1</link>
  <link href="#changes_1.1.0">Version 1.1.0</link>
  <link href="#changes_1.0.1">Version 1.0.1</link>
</link>
<link href="#misc">Miscelleanous</link>
<link href="#contact">Contact</link>
</table-of-content>

<section name="what_is" label="About Autopoweroff">

<p>

  Autopoweroff is daemon that is started at boot time, and which
  function is to shutdown the computer at a specific time, but 
  only if some conditions are met.  This software is meant for
  the Linux operating system.

</p>
<p>

  The computer will shutdown if all the above conditions are met:

</p>

<ul>

    <li>

    Any hosts that the computer is dependant on is not
    answering ping anymore.

    </li>

    <li>

    No keyboard or mouse activity has been detected on the computer for
    a while.

    </li>

    <li>

    The user has not disabled Autopoweroff.

    </li>

</ul>

<p>

  One good use of Autopoweroff is for home use, on a firewall/router
  server.  You can setup Autopoweroff to shutdown the server every
  evening at say, 22:00.  However, your server might serve other
  computers in your home.  Autopoweroff will shutdown the server after
  22:00 only if no other computer on the network is responding to
  <code>ping</code>.  For example, if at 22:43 you are still working on
  your thin client in the living room, the server in your baseman will
  remain up.  As soon as you shutdown the workstation, the server will
  go down.

</p>
<p>

  The server can boot automatically every morning by setting its BIOS
  properly.  Autopoweroff has nothing to do with this process.  But with
  this setting, your home server does not need to run 24/7.  The advantages
  such a setting offers are:

  <ul>

    <li>

      Increase security.  Nobody can hack your server while its shutdown.

    </li>
    <li>

      Save electricity and curb down heat generation.

    </li>
    <li>

      Cut down noise.  A shutdown server does not produce any noise.

    </li>
    <li>

      Avoid the hassle of having to shut down and start up the server
      manually.

    </li>
  </ul>

</p>
<p>

  A nice GUI is provided to configure Autopoweroff's parameters.  See
  <section-link href="#config_autopoweroff_gui">Autopoweroff configurator</section-link>.

</p>
<p>

  The SourceForge page for this project can be found 
  <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/autopoweroff/">here</a>.

</p>

<!--
<table width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" width="130">

      <p class="warning">
        HELP WANTED
      </p>

    </td>
    <td>

      <p>

      USB keyboards and mice are not yet supported.  I simply do not know
      how to implement activity detection with these devices.  If you have
      any clue how to do this, please share your ideas with me.

      </p>

    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
-->


</section>

<section name="distributions" label="Supported Linux distributions">

<p>

  Autopoweroff will work on most distributions.  However, for some
  distribution you might have to manually move files to the right place
  to get it working and write your own init script so that Autopoweroff
  would start at booting.  If you install Autopoweroff from the tarball,
  this is more likely.

</p>
<p>

  Fully supported distributions include:  <b>Ubuntu</b>, <b>Fedora</b>,
  <b>Red Hat</b>.  It should also work with <b>Debian</b> and
  <b>Mandrake</b>.  Download the .rpm or .deb package and everything
  will be installed and enabled automatically.  This include setting up
  Autopoweroff to start at the next computer boot.  And if you decide
  to remove Autopoweroff, everything gets removed.

</p>
<p>

  With a package, you will only have to run the GUI configuration tool or
  edit <code>/etc/autopoweroff.conf</code> to your particular needs.

  Autopoweroff will be submitted to Ubuntu's and Fedora's repositories,
  making it even easier to install it.

</p>
<table width="100%">
  <tr>
  <td valign="top" width="130">
    <p class="warning">
    HELP WANTED
    </p>
    </td>
    <td>

    <p>

    If you are running a distribution that is not yet supported by
    Autopoweroff, write to me.  I will ask you some questions about your
    distribution and probably be able to add support for it.

    </p>

  </td>
  </tr>
</table>

</section>


<section name="download" label="Download">

<p>

  The latest version of Autopoweroff can be downloaded from
  <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=74727">
  SourceForge</a>.

<table width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td valign="top" width="130">

      <p class="warning">
        ALPHA VERSION AVAILABLE.
      </p>

    </td>
    <td>

      <p>

        Version 2.9.0 is an alpha version (3.0.0 will be the stable
        release).  I need people to test it.  Unknown bugs might cause
        your system to shutdown even if someone is making use of it.
        However, 2.9.0 appears stable and I suggest people to try it
        out.

      <p>
      </p>

        Please provide feedback by writing to me at
        <a href="mailto:hans@deragon.biz">hans@deragon.biz</a>
        If enough people report to me that this version is stable, I
        will release it as such.

      </p>

    </td>
  </tr>
</table>

</p>

</section>

<section name="configuration" label="Configuration">
<br/>

  Following are subsections that explains how to configure your system for
  Autopoweroff.

</section>

<section name="config_autopoweroff" label="Autopoweroff configuration">

<p>
  There are two ways to configure Autopoweroff.

  <ul>
    <li>
      Use the <section-link href="#config_autopoweroff_gui">GUI configuration tool</section-link>.

    </li>
    <li>
      Edit manually the configuration file <section-link href="#config_autopoweroff_file"><code>autopoweroff.conf</code></section-link>.
    </li>
  </ul>
</p>

Following, the list of sub-sections.

</section>

<section name="config_autopoweroff_gui" label="Autopoweroff GUI configuration tool">

<p>

  The Autopoweroff GUI configuration tool is pretty easy.

</p>
<p>

  In the first panel named <em>Status &amp; Commands</em>,
  the user can enable or disable Autopoweroff and poweroff
  or reboot the computer.

</p>

<blockquote>
<table>
  <tr width="600">
    <td align="center">
      <img src="autopoweroff_cfg-statusandcmd.png" alt="Status &amp; Commands screenshot"/>
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td align="center">
      <i>Status &amp; commands</i>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
</blockquote>
<p>

  In the second panel named <em>Status &amp; Commands</em>, the user can
  configure the different parameters of Autopoweroff.  See <section-link
  href="#config_autopoweroff_file">Autopoweroff configuration
  file</section-link> for a description of the different parameters.

</p>
<blockquote>
<table>
  <tr width="600">
    <td align="center">
      <img src="autopoweroff_cfg-config.png" alt="Configuration screenshot"/>
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td align="center">
      <i>Configuration</i>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
</blockquote>
<p align="center">


</p>

</section>


<section name="config_autopoweroff_file" label="Autopoweroff configuration file (autopoweroff.conf)">

<p>

  The <code>/etc/autopoweroff.conf</code> (or
  <code>${prefix}/etc/autopoweroff.conf</code>, for those who installed
  from the tarball) configuration file is well documented and easy to
  understand.  Following is an example:

</p>

<blockquote>
<pre>
# Autopoweroff X.Y.Z configuration file.
                                                                                
# WARNING:  If you decide to edit this file, edit only the values of the
#           parameters.  If you add comments, they will be lost at the
#           next software upgrade or when the GUI configurator is being
#           used to update the file.  Only values persists.
                                                                                
                                                                                
# start and end parameters (expressed in hours):
#
#   Following is the time range where the computer should not shutdown
#   even if all conditions are met.  In this example where start=5 and
#   end=22, the computer will not shut down between 05:00 and 22:00,
#   local time.
                                                                                
[NO_SHUTDOWN_TIME_RANGE]
start=5
end=22
                                                                                
                                                                                
# startup_delay parameter (expressed in minutes):
#
#   When the computer is booting up, if all the conditions are met and
#   the computer is in the shutdown time range, as soon as Autopoweroff
#   is started, the computer will shutdown.  Thus, the user will never
#   have the chance to boot into the computer.  This is where the
#   "delay" parameter comes in.  If "delay" is set to 15 for example,
#   Autopoweroff will not poweroff the computer even if all the
#   conditions are met, for a period of 15 minutes after the computer
#   has booted.  This allows the user to login and change Autopoweroff's
#   configuration.
#
#
# idle_time parameter (expressed in minutes):
#
#   Like a screensaver, Autopoweroff detects keyboard and mouse
#   activity, and if there is any activity on the server, it would not
#   be powered off regardless if all the other conditions are met.  If
#   set to 0, user activity on the server will be ignored.
#
#   For the moment, PS/2 keyboards and PS/2 &amp; serial mices have been tested.
#   Unfortunatly, USB keyboards and mices are not supported yet (I do not
#   know how to implement activity detection on these devices).  

[TIMEOUTS]
startup_delay=15
idle_time=5
                                                                                
                                                                                
# host parameter (list of hostnames or IPs, separated by commas):
#
#   Here you list the list of hosts your machine is dependant, i.e. this
#   computer should not shutdown if any of the hosts declared here is
#   still up (responding to ping).
                                                                                
[DEPENDANTS]
hosts=snahwin, snah
</pre>
</blockquote>


</section>

<section name="config_bios" label="BIOS configuration">

<p>

  It is possible to setup the BIOS so that the computer will boot
  itself every day.  Each BIOS is different, but they are pretty much
  similar.  Following are the instructions on how to setup an Award
  BIOS.

</p>
<p>

  On the main page, select the menu <em>POWER</em>, then the
  <em>POWER UP CONTROL</em> item.  Once the new screen shows up,
  move the cursor to the <em>Automatic Power Up</em> line and select
  <em>Everyday</em>.  On the following line, set the time at which
  the computer should start everyday.  Save the settings and voilà.

</p>

</section>



<section name="installation" label="Installation">

<p>

  To install the .deb package, simply run:

</p>

<blockquote>
  <code>
  sudo dpkg -i autopoweroff*.deb  
  </code>
</blockquote>

<p>

  To install the .rpm package, simply run:

</p>

<blockquote>
  <code>
  rpm -Uhv autopoweroff*.rpm
  </code>
</blockquote>

<p>

  For the tarball, extract it and run <code>configure</code> followed
  by <code>make install</code>.

</p>

<blockquote>
  <code>

  tar xvzf autopoweroff.tar.gz
<br/>
  cd autopoweroff
<br/>
  configure --prefix="&lt;path to the installation directory&gt;"
<br/>
  make install

  </code>
</blockquote>

<p> 

  You will need to setup the init script properly.  Two versions exists.

</p> 
</section>

<section name="uninstallation" label="Uninstallation">

<p>

  To uninstall the .deb package, simply run:

</p>

<blockquote>
  <code>
  sudo dpkg -r autopoweroff
  </code>
</blockquote>

<p>

  To uninstall the .rpm package, simply run:

</p>

<blockquote>
  <code>
  rpm -e autopoweroff
  </code>
</blockquote>

<p>

  If you installed from the tarball, run
</p>

<blockquote>
  <code>
  autopoweroff_uninstall
  </code>
</blockquote>
</section>

<section name="license" label="License">
<p>

  This software is covered by the 

  <a href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html#TOC1">GPL 2.0</a>

  license.  For a local copy of the license, see file
  COPYING.

</p>
</section>


<section name="troubleshooting" label="Troubleshooting">
<p>
  Following are troubleshooting sections.

  <ul>
    <li>
      <section-link href="#troubleshooting_glade">Troubleshooting Glade warnings</section-link>.
    </li>
  </ul>
</p>
</section>
<section name="troubleshooting_glade" label="Troubleshooting Glade warnings">

  <p>
    Do not be alarmed by glade warning message showing up when you
    are running the <code>autopoweroff</code> command (the GUI configurator).
    These warning appears because you are running a different version of
    Gnome than the one upon which Autopoweroff was built.  Probably you
    are running an older version, thus some new properties that were
    introduced are not supported on your older system.  For instance,
    On a Fedora Core 4 system, you will get the following errors:

  </p>
  <p><code>
(autopoweroff:5954): libglade-WARNING **: unknown property `urgency_hint' for class `GtkDialog'
    </code></p>
    <p><code>
(autopoweroff:5954): libglade-WARNING **: unknown property `wrap_license' for class `GtkAboutDialog'
  </code></p>
  <p>
    This is nothing to be concerned about.
  </p>
</section>

<section name="developers" label="For Developers">
  <br/>

  Autopoweroff might be of interest to developers because of the following
  reasons:
  
  <br/>
  <ul>
  <li>

    This project is a very nice example on how to write a Python daemon
    that probes input devices, make use of threads

  </li>
  <li>

    It is also a very good example about packaging for .deb and .rpm
    based distributions, and universal tarball.  It makes heavy use of
    autoconf and automake.

  </li>
  <li>

    Finally, be this project a lesson;  if you distribute your software
    with a tarball, provide an easy solution to de-install it.  Either
    provide a script like Autopoweroff is doing, or provide a "make
    uninstall" target.

  </li>
  </ul>

</section>

<section name="todo" label="To do">

<p>

The following are features to be added in future releases.

</p>

<ul>

  <li>

    Detect activity from a remote login, either it be console or an X session.
    Currently, if someone is working remotly on the computer, this will go
    undetected and Autopoweroff will proceed with the shutdown if all other
    conditions are met.

  </li>
  <li>

    Internationalization (i18n).  Autopoweroff is currently available only
    in English.

  </li>
  <li>

    New GUI that follows more closely the Gnome recommendations.

  </li>
  <li>

    Better documentation, including writing a man page.

  </li>
  <li>

    Support for a wider range of Linux distributions.

  </li>
</ul>

</section>

<section name="change_history" label="Change history">

<br/>

The following changes have been incorporated in the below mentioned versions:


</section>

<section name="changes_3.0.0" label="Version 2.9.0 - 2008/??/??">

<br/>
This release is a complete overhaul of the project.
<br/>

<ul>

  <li>

    Ubuntu support introduced.

  </li>
  <li>

    New technics are used to probe device, which now include USB devices.
    For the techies, /dev/input/by-path devices get probed.
    Modern kernels are required.

  </li>
  <li>

    Subversion is now used instead of CVS for software configuration
    management.

  </li>

</ul>
</section>

<section name="changes_2.1.0" label="Version 2.1.0 - 2004/01/19">

<ul>

  <li>

    Like a screensaver, Autopoweroff now detects idle time on the server
    by scanning for keyboard and mouse activity.  Currently, PS/2
    keyboards and PS/2 &amp; serial mices are supported (USB devices are
    unfortunatly not detected yet).

  </li>

  <li>

    Added automatic configuration file upgrade.  If you upgrade Autopoweroff
    and autopoweroff.conf configuration file format has changed, it will
    automatically be upgraded to the new format while preserving the
    previous configuration.

  </li>

  <li>

    If Autopoweroff, upon startup, discovers that another instance of
    itself is already running, instead of quiting it kills the old
    instance and continues.

  </li>

  <li>

    Replaced calls to "reboot" and "poweroff" with their corresponding
    "shutdown" command.  Some user wrote to me asking where reboot and
    poweroff could be obtained, so I assume that they are not always
    available.

  </li>


</ul>
</section>

<section name="changes_2.0.0" label="Version 2.0.0 - 2003/11/23">

<ul>

  <li>

    Created a user interface to simplify configuration.  See
    <section-link href="#config_autopoweroff_gui">
      Autopoweroff GUI configuration tool
    </section-link>.

  </li>

  <li>

    Miscelleanous Autopoweroff events are now reported in syslog, for
    tracking purposes.

  </li>

  <li>

    Removed Gnome dependency, for servers running in text mode only.

  </li>


</ul>

</section>
<section name="changes_1.2.0" label="Version 1.2.0 - 2003/06/07">

<ul>

  <li>

    Fixed *.desktop files so that the icons now appear in the gnome
    "system tools" menu even if no locale is set.

  </li>

</ul>

</section>

<section name="changes_1.1.1" label="Version 1.1.1 - 2003/05/03">

<ul>

  <li>

    RPM installation now fully recognize Mandrake.

  </li>

  <li>

    Improved the Autopoweroff Configuration section of the document and
    the comments in /etc/autopoweroff.conf.

  </li>

  <li>

    Added the <code>Supported distributions</code> section.

  </li>

</ul>

</section>

<section name="changes_1.1.0" label="Version 1.1.0 - 2003/04/27">

<ul>

  <li>

    Automatic Gnome installation.  Under Red Hat 9.0, the cancel and
    enable scripts now have icons showing up under the "System tools"
    menu.

  </li>

  <li>

    Improved the installation and uninstallation of the software from
    a tarball.

  </li>

</ul>

</section>

<section name="changes_1.0.1" label="Version 1.0.1 - 2003/04/14">

<ul>

  <li>

    Used autoconf to allow installation from a tarball.

  </li>

  <li>

    Started using <a href="http://aurigadoc.sourceforge.net/">AurigaDoc</a>
    for creating this document.

  </li>

</ul>

</section>
<section name="misc" label="Miscelleanous">
  This document has been created <a href="http://aurigadoc.sourceforge.net/">AurigaDoc</a>
</section>

<section name="contact" label="Contact">

<p>

  If you have any questions or issues with this software, you can contact
  the following persons:

</p>


<blockquote>
<table>
  <tr>
    <td>
      Author:
    </td>
    <td>
      Hans Deragon
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>
      Email:
    </td>
    <td>
      <a href="mailto:hans@deragon.biz">hans@deragon.biz</a>
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>
      Website: 
    </td>
    <td>
      <a href="http://www.deragon.biz">www.deragon.biz</a>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>
</blockquote>

</section>
</document-body>
</document>
